Delaney, James Joseph; Papers apap241
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
James Joseph Delaney Papers
1950-1978
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Delaney, James Joseph, 1901-1987.
apap241
11.65 cubic ft. processed to date
The James Joseph Delaney Papers, 1950-1978, document Delaney’s extensive tenure in Congress. Elected in November 1948, Delaney remained in Congress until his retirement in December 1978. Delaney served as Congressman from Queens, New York and his three decades in Washington are distinguished by consecutive elections to chairman of the House Rules Committee and the addition of the 1958 Delaney Clause to the 1938 Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by James Joseph Delaney in 1978.
Biographical Sketch
James Joseph Delaney was born in New York City on March 19, 1901. He attended public schools in Long Island City, Queens and in 1931 received a law degree from St. John’s University. Between 1936 and 1944, Delaney served as an assistant to the Queens District Attorney’s office. Elected as a Democrat to the Seventy-ninth Congress in November 1944, Delaney was an unsuccessful candidate for reelection in 1946 and resumed his law career thereafter. Delaney’s hiatus from politics was short-lived following his election to the 81 st United States Congress in 1948. Having been reelected to 14 succeeding congresses Delaney served as Congressman from Queens, New York from January 3, 1949 until his retirement on December 31, 1978.
Delaney is noted for his campaign to have cancer-causing agents banned from food, drugs and cosmetics. Passed in 1958, the Delaney Amendment was a clause in the 1938 Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act that outlawed cancer-causing additives in food and commenced the federal government’s role in protecting the public from cancer. His amendment required the Food and Drug Administration to monitor for any chemical additives in food that were found to induce cancer in man or animals. Delaney became involved with this issue as chairman of the Select House Committee that conducted an investigation and study of the use of chemicals, pesticides, and insecticides in and with respect to food products in January 1949 and again in January 1951. In 1996 Congress amended the Delaney Clause with the Food Quality Protection Act (FQPA) that changed the “zero risk” standard, which made no allowances, to one of “reasonable certainty.”
Delaney was frequently at odds with fellow Democrats over his votes against federal aid to education, support for public aid to parochial schools, school busing, and his support of the Vietnam War. As chairman of the New York City Congressional delegation in the mid-1970’s, he played a key role in shaping the federal legislation that helped rescue the city from its financial crisis by securing a 2.4 billion dollar low-interest loan. His three decades in Washington catapulted him into the chairmanship of the powerful Committee on Rules in January 1977.
Delaney married Lola Mathis in 1939 and had a son, Patrick. Following his retirement in 1978 James Joseph Delaney was a resident of Key Biscayne, Florida until his death at his son’s home in Tenafly, New Jersey on May 24, 1987. Interment was in Calvary Cemetery, Queens, New York.
Scope and Contents
The James Joseph Delaney Collection consists of 11.65 cubic feet and is arranged into two series. Series 1: Legislative Files is divided into three Sub-series: Sub-series 1: Chemical Additives in Food and Drug contains legislative files, news clippings and correspondence from Delaney’s campaign to have cancer-causing agents banned from food, drugs and cosmetics; Sub-series 2: Education Files focuses on Delaney’s support of Federal Aid for public and private education including the tuition voucher system and consists of news clippings, House Resolution (H.R.) jackets, and correspondence; and Sub-series 3: Subject Files consist of statements, releases, H.R. jackets and correspondence that relate to various political issues of interest to Delaney.
During his terms in Congress Delaney encountered a variety of legislative issues concerning chemical additives in foods and federal aid to education. In January 1949 and again in January 1951, Delaney became chairman of the Select House Committee which conducted an investigation and study of the use of chemicals, pesticides, and insecticides in and with respect to food products. Sub-series 1: Chemical Additives in Food and Drug includes news clippings, publications by Delaney and others, reports, and correspondence all of which are related to the fight against cancer-causing agents in food, drugs, and cosmetics. This series includes documents on antibiotics, asbestos, and fluoridation. Also included are correspondence, endorsements, hearings, releases and speech notes from the Select House Committee.
In 1952, growing concern over funding for private and public education led to Delaney’s involvement in a campaign for federal aid to education. Subseries 2: Education Files, includes correspondence, Congressional files, news clippings, publications, press releases, and statements by Delaney and others. Delaney corresponds with individuals and organizations about aid to private and public education. Notable correspondents include Hugh L. Carey, Cardinal Spellman and the Citizens for Educational Freedom. Delaney’s support for aid to education is well documented through his support of the Junior G.I. bill, a tuition tax credit, and the voucher system. Sub-series 3: Subject Files consist of statements, releases, H.R. jackets and correspondence that relate to other political issues. The folders in this series include H.R. jackets accompanied by correspondence, news clippings, press releases, and statements related to the issue. Each folder in this series concerns a potential legislation and includes related materials for decision makers. Topics include immigration, political prisoners, social security, taxes and much more.
Series 2: Communications includes speeches, statements and press releases given by Delaney and others. We retained a list of all H.R. jackets that Delaney was involved with but have disposed of the originals. As a representative from New York, Delaney had a continuous interaction with the media. Between 1958 and 1978, communication between Delaney’s office and the public were well documented. He issued press releases, speeches, statements, and other communication on many relevant topics. He discussed education, food additives, abortion, social security, the international drug trade and much more. Folders with H.R. jackets include correspondence and Delaney’s notes. Also, Series 1 contains audio and visual material, including an open reel recording and transcript of an August 1957, ABC interview, As We See It. The collection also includes transcripts of the ABC interview, a June 1962 NBC television and radio broadcast of Meet the Press with Abraham Ribicoff, and an April 1963 CBS broadcast The Silent Spring of Rachel Carson.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Legislative Files, 1950-1978
Series 2 - Communications, 1956-1978, Arranged chronologically, 2 cubic ft.
The folders in this series are arranged chronologically and include speeches, statements, press releases and other communication between Delaney’s office and the media. Folders with H.R. jackets include correspondence and Delaney’s notes. Topics of statements and press releases include abortion, social security, and the international drug trade.
Public Servants; Politics and Politicians; Legislators--United States; Food additives; Federal aid to education--United States; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence; Press Releases; Legislative materials; Delaney, James Joseph
- Legislative Files, 1950-1978, 1; 9.65 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Legislative Files is divided into three Sub-series: Sub-series 1: Chemical Additives in Food and Drug contains legislative files, news clippings and correspondence from Delaney’s campaign to have cancer-causing agents banned from food, drugs and cosmetics; Sub-series 2: Education Files focuses on Delaney’s support of Federal Aid for public and private education including the tuition voucher system and consists of news clippings, House Resolution (H.R.) jackets, and correspondence; and Sub-series 3: Subject Files consist of statements, releases, H.R. jackets and correspondence that relate to various political issues of interest to Delaney.
  Sub-series 1: Chemical Additives in Food and Drug includes news clippings, publications by Delaney and others, reports, and correspondence all of which are related to the fight against cancer-causing agents in food, drugs, and cosmetics. This series includes documents on antibiotics, asbestos, and fluoridation. Also included are correspondence, endorsements, hearings, releases and speech notes from the Select House Committee.
  Subseries 2: Education Files, includes correspondence, Congressional files, news clippings, publications, press releases, and statements by Delaney and others. Delaney corresponds with individuals and organizations about aid to private and public education. Notable correspondents include Hugh L. Carey, Cardinal Spellman and the Citizens for Educational Freedom. Delaney’s support for aid to education is well documented through his support of the Junior G.I. bill, a tuition tax credit, and the voucher system.
  Sub-series 3: Subject Files consist of statements, releases, H.R. jackets and correspondence that relate to other political issues. The folders in this series include H.R. jackets accompanied by correspondence, news clippings, press releases, and statements related to the issue. Each folder in this series concerns a potential legislation and includes related materials for decision makers. Topics include immigration, political prisoners, social security, taxes and much more.
  - Chemical Additives in Food and Drug, 1950-1978; 1.1
    - Albright, Eugene, fluoridation, 1963 March-1966 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 1)
    - Anderson, Ernest, Greater New York Committee Opposed to Fluoridation, 1963-1972 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 2)
    - Antibiotics in animal feed, Department of Health Education and Welfare (Department of Health and Human Services), 1973, 1973 April 19 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 3)
    - Asbestos 1973, 1973 July-1973 November (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 4)
    - As We See It, ABC interview. Includes open reel audio and transcript, 1957 August (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 5)
    - Ask, Dr. David, fluoridation, 1971 July (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 6)
    - Astarita, Salvatore M., health foods, 1968 March (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 7)
    - Atlas of Cancer Mortality for U.S. Countries, 1950-1969 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 8)
    - Blaszczak, Dr. Joseph, National Cancer Institute grant application, December 1965-March 1973, 1965 December-1973 March (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 9)
    - Bryan, Dr. George, 1970 August-1970 September (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 10)
    - Cancer and the environment, 1976 January (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 11)
    - Cancer information crusade, 1975 August-1975 October (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 12)
    - Cancer publications, 1970-1973 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 13)
    - Chemical additives, 1951-1957 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 14)
    - Chemical additives, 1958-1960 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 15)
    - Chemical additives, 1961-1967 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 16)
    - Chemical additives, 1969-1972 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 17)
    - Chemical additives bill and report requests, 1955 March-December (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 18)
    - Chemical additives, aflatoxin, 1973-1974 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 19)
    - Chemical additives, carrageenan/cyclamates, 1972-1974 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 20)
    - Chemical additives legislation, January 1953-May 1957, 1953 January-1957 May (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 21)
    - Clippings, drug crisis, August 1970-July 1971, 1970 August-1971 July (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 22)
    - Clippings, Food and Drug Administration antibiotic scandal, 1960-1962 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 23)
    - Clippings, fluoridation, 1952-1965 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 24)
    - Clippings, food additives, 1970-1972 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 25)
    - Clippings, tobacco and cancer, 1964 March-1964 April (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 26)
    - Coal tar hair dyes, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 27)
    - Color additives (general). Includes statements, clippings, TV show transcript, 1957-1963 (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 28)
    - Color additives legislation, 1959 June-1964 July (Box 1 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 29)
    - Congressional Research Service (CRS), 1972 July (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 1)
    - "Congressional Close-up", WCBS-TV and WCBS Radio, program transcript. Interview with Congressman James J. Delaney (NY), Congressman Frank C. Osmers (NJ), Congressman Alfred Santangelo (NY), and Congressman Vincent J. Dellay (NJ)., 1957 May 11 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 1A)
    - Consumer Protection Act of 1970, H.R. 18214, April-December 1970, 1970 April-1970 December (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 2)
    - Consumer study (Davenport), 1952-1961 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 3)
    - Cosmetics, 1962 May-1962 September (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 4)
    - Cosmetics CRS Info, 1978 January-1978 June (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 5)
    - Cyclamate and saccharin, undated (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 6-7)
    - DDT ration in foods, 1966 January-1971 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 8)
    - Delaney Amendment. Includes photographs., 1970-1978 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 9-11)
    - De Munn, M.F., 1960 January-1960 June (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 12)
    - Department of Agriculture, 1970 February (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 13)
    - Department of Health Education and Welfare (Department of Health and Human Services), Cyclamates and saccharin, 1969-1973 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 14)
    - Department of Health Education and Welfare (Department of Health and Human Services), food additives, 1959 April-1962 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 15-16)
    - Department of Health Education and Welfare (Department of Health and Human Services), Kefauver-Harris Drug Amendment of 1962, 1962 October (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 17)
    - Desmond, Ruth, Federation of Homemakers, 1962-1972 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 18)
    - Diethylstilbestrol (DES), 1971 October-1977 February (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 19-20)
    - Diethylstilbestrol (DES) and early attacks on the Delaney Amendment, 1956 January-1962 (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 21)
    - Drug and narcotic documents, September 1969-April 1973, 1969 September-1973 April (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 22-24)
    - Drug and narcotic traffic, documents/notes, 1970 May-1971 June (Box 2 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 25-26)
    - Drug Industry Act of 1962, S. 1552, 87th Congress, 1962 July-1962 October (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 1)
    - Finch, Secretary Robert H., cyclamates, 1969-1970 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 2)
    - Fish flour, 1961 September (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 3)
    - Flood, Daniel J., 1975-1976 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 4)
    - Flood, Daniel J., hearings on National Cancer Institute, 1976 February (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 5)
    - Fluoridation, 1960-1972 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 6-8)
    - Fluoridation, 1975-1976 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 9-11)
    - Fluoridation and drinking water, 1977 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 12-14)
    - Fluoridation defense, 1975 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 15)
    - Food additives, 1969-1973 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 16)
    - Food additives. Testimony on nitrites, Congressional Research Service, and generally recognized as safe in foods list review, 1977 January-June (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 17)
    - Food additives, 1978 February-1978 August (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 18)
    - Food additives, amendments published in the Federal Register, 1962-1969 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 19-20)
    - Food additives, Judiciary Committee, 1970-1974 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 21)
    - Food additives, National Academy of Science, 1973 March-1973 May (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 22)
    - Food additives, White House report, 1960 May (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 23)
    - Food and Drug Act, 1962 August (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 24)
    - Food and Drug Administration, April 1970-February 1971, 1970 April-1971 February (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 25-26)
    - Food and Drug Administration Museum Select Committee to Investigate the Use of Chemicals in Foods and Cosmetics, 1950-1952 (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 27)
    - Food and drug research laboratories, 1962 August (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 28)
    - Food, drug, and cosmetic legislation, 88th, 1963 January-1963 November (Box 3 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 29)
    - Food labeling regulations, 1972-1973 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 1-2)
    - Food Protection Act of 1972, S. 3163, 3295, 406, 91st -92nd, 1969 December-1973 January (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 3)
    - Food Protection Committee, 1956 November-1959 December (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 4)
    - Food safety, 1971 January (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 5)
    - Fountain, L.H., 1975 August (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 6)
    - Generally recognized as safe in foods (GRAS) list, 1971 January (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 7)
    - Generic v. prescription drugs, November 1975-June 1978, 1975 November-1978 June (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 8)
    - Glycine, January-May 1970, 1970 January-1970 May (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 9)
    - H.R. 366, 4432, 7700, 8112, 8390, 8629, 13254, Federal Food, Drug and Cosmetic Act, 85th, January 1957- June 1958; H.R. 9521, To Define Chemical Preservative, 85th Congress, July 1958; H.R. 12437, Animal Feed, 87th Congress, July 1962;H.R. 11581, Drug Bill, 87th Congress, September 1962; H.R. 10409, 6846, Drug Bill, 88th Congress, June 1963-March 1964; H.R. 18074, Drug Bill, 91st Congress 1969-1970; H.R. 1235 Food, Drug, Cosmetic Amendments of 1967; H.R. 7798, 2245, 4475, 4014, Food additives bills, 83rd-85th January 1953-May 1957; H.R. 7042, 89th, Confectionery, April 1965; H.R. 5777, 5661, Cosmetic Bills, 88th, April 1963; H.R. 4990, Food Additive Pre-market Clearance, 92nd, February 1971, 1957-1971 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 10)
    - Health Bulletin, 1966-1967 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 11)
    - Hueper, Dr. Wilhelm C., 1959-1970 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 12)
    - Insecticide, Fungicide and Rodenticide Act Amendments, October 1963, 1963 October (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 13)
    - International Union against Cancer Symposium, Rome, 1958 August (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 14)
    - Jerard, Elise, 1970-1975 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 15)
    - Kalade, Dr. Peter, 1973 April-1973 May (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 16)
    - Kelsey, Dr. Francis O., Food and Drug Administration and thalidomide, 1962 August-1962 September (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 17)
    - Kepone correspondence, 1976 January (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 18)
    - Laetrile, 1977 February (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 19)
    - La Vine, Louis A., 1966 January (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 20)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1963 December (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 21)
    - Meyer, Dr. Grace Townsend, 1970 February (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 22)
    - Mick, Dr. Robert H., correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 23)
    - Mick, Dr. Robert H., summary of Piess communications, 1971-1972 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 24)
    - Mick, Dr. Robert H., fluoridation background material, Undated (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 25)
    - Mider, Dr. G.B., 1970 August (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 26)
    - Mirex, Kenneth Grant, 1971 September-1971 October (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 27)
    - Mobbs, Dr. Robert F., 1969-1971 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 28)
    - Muckerman, Chris J., 1970-1972 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 29)
    - National Cancer Act, S. 1828, 91st-92nd, 1970 April-1971 December (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 30)
    - National Cancer Institute, report on 2, 4-diaminoanisole sulfate, 1978 January (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 31-32)
    - National Cancer Program, 1977 June (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 33)
    - National Commission on Water Quality, November 1975-March 1976, 1975 November-1976 March (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 34)
    - National Health Federation, 1970-1972 (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 35-36)
    - National Health Federation, misc. correspondence, 1975 July-1976 December (Box 4 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 37)
    - National Health Promotion and Disease Prevention Act of 1976 (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 1)
    - N.Y. state chemical additive legislation, proposed, 1957-1959 (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 2)
    - N.Y. stock exchange rule 394, 1975 November (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 3)
    - Organic Consumer Report, 1969-1972 (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 4)
    - “Peril on Your Food Shelf” by Delaney, 1951 July (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 5)
    - Pesticides, 1965-1971 (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 6-7)
    - “The Poisons in Your Food”, 1960 March (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 8)
    - Publications, 1958 June-970 (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 9)
    - Recycling, 1971 June (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 10)
    - Red dye no. 2, 1975 October-1977 January (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 11)
    - Richardson, Dr. Howard L., 1970 August (Box 5 (1-Legislative Files, 1950-1978), Folder 12)